Inventory of the Nell Eurich papers 1922-2000
Hoover Institution Archives
Nell Eurich papers
1922-2000
2000C82
Hoover Institution Archives
135 manuscript boxes (54.0 linear feet)
The collection includes speeches and writings, correspondence, memoranda, studies, reports, and printed matter related to international and comparative education, higher education in the United States, adult education and literacy, career and job training, and corporate involvement in education. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Eurich, Nell.
Arrangement
Description is based on a detailed container list provided by Nell Eurich and found in box 111, folder 4. Since the collection has not been physically arranged, the order of materials differs from Eurich's container list. The index of major groups can serve as a guide to the collection. Most folder headings are original.
Index of Major Groups
111 Collection overview and biographical file, undated. Includes detailed container list of the Nell Eurich papers and curriculum vitae of Eurich. Includes one floppy disk.
87-89, 111-114, 124-127 Speeches and writings, 1937-1995. Includes monographs, typescripts, and printed matter related to education. See International Council for Educational Development for files on Systems of Higher Education in 12 Countries.
17-20, 84-87, 89-95, 115-119, 121-125 Professional positions and activities file, 1966-2000. Includes correspondence, meeting minutes, printed matter, research material, course materials, and awards related to Eurich's various professional positions, including materials for New College, Vassar College, and the International Council for Educational Development.
120-121 Other activities file, 1941-1992. Includes correspondence, clippings, and photographs related to community service and the Campobello Summer Student Leadership Institute. Includes photographs of Eleanor Roosevelt.
108-110 Correspondence, 1964-1997. Consists of two subseries: noteworthy correspondents and general.
85-98, 105-108, 110-111, 127-130 Corporate Classrooms file, 1928-1999. Includes research material, drafts, correspondence, and printed matter for the Corporate Classrooms study funded by the Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching.
4-17, 20-32, 36-55, 59-64, 66-68, 71-74, 77-84, 98-105 The Learning Industry and Adult Learning Project file, 1922-1999. Includes correspondence, memoranda, research material, drafts, notes, printed matter, brochures, and clippings related to the project and publication.
1-3, 33-36, 56-58, 65, 68-71, 74-77 Education, training, and technology file, 1963-1996. Includes correspondence, memoranda, clippings, and printed matter related to various topics in education, including innovative education.
Access
Collection is open for research. Collection stored off site; a minimum of two days notice is required for use. Boxes may be requested through Stanford's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible. The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2000.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Related Collections
Alvin C. Eurich papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Academy For Educational Development records, Hoover Institution Archives
International Council For Educational Development records, Hoover Institution Archives
Biographical Note
1919 July 28 Born, Norwood, Ohio
1939 A.A., Stephens College
1941 B.A., Stanford University
1941 Attended Campobello Summer Student Leadership Institute held at the summer house of Eleanor Roosevelt
1942-1943 Director of the student union, University of Texas
1943 M.A., Stanford University
1944-1946 Resident counselor, Barnard College
1947-1949 Assistant to president, Women's Foundation
1949-1951 Assistant public relations officer, State University of New York
1951-1952 Assistant for organizing the overseas division, Ford Foundation
1952 Acting president, Stephens College, Columbia, Missouri
1953 Married Alvin C. Eurich
1953-1954 Director of development, Stephens College, Columbia, Missouri
1959 Ph.D., Columbia University
1959-1964 Assistant professor of English, New York University
1962 Member of an advisory committee to design curriculum for New College, Sarasota, Florida
1965 Academic dean and acting president, New College, Sarasota, Florida
1965-1975 Trustee, New College, Sarasota, Florida
1966 Director, Project to Reorganize Curriculum, Aspen Public High School, Colorado
1966-1967 Member, National Selection Committee on Fellowships and Chairman, Rocky Mountain Committee, National Endowment for the Humanities
1966-1970 Member, Special Committee on Liberal Studies, American Association of Colleges
1967 Author, Science in Utopia
1967 Author, "Learning in America," published in From Parnassus: A Volume of Essays for Jacques Barzun
1967-1970 Dean of faculty, professor of English, academic director of the Vassar-Yale study and chairman of the Comprehensive Planning Committee, Vassar College, New York
1967-1971 Member, Middle States Committee, Marshall Scholarships
1968-1969 Member, U.S. Commission on Instructional Technology, U.S. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare
1969 Member, Panel of Judges, Federal Woman's Award
1969 Honorary member, National Council of Women
1969-1975 Member, Overseers Visiting Committee on Summer School and University Extension, Harvard University
1970-1971 Consultant for Manhattanville grant application, National Endowment for the Humanities
1971 Author, Great Britain's Open University: First Chance, Second Chance, or Last Chance? (co-authored with B. Schwenkmeyer)
1971-1975 Provost and dean of faculty, professor of English, and vice president for academy affairs, Manhattanville College, New York
1972 Member, Career Minister Review Board, U.S. Department of State
1974 Contributing author, Learning for Tomorrow
1975 Received honorary Doctor of Humane Letters degree from Manhattanville College, New York
1975-1993 Senior consultant, board member and executive committee member, and director of the Comparative Study of Higher Education Systems in Twelve Countries, International Council for Educational Development
1975-circa 2001 Trustee, New College Foundation
1976 Member, Middle Atlantic Committee, Rhodes Scholarship Selection Committee
1977, 1979-1980 Moderator, Corporate Executive Seminar, Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies
1977-1980 Member, Carnegie Council on Policy Studies in Higher Education
1977-1990 Trustee, Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching
1978 Editor, Systems of Higher Education, International Council for Educational Development
1979-1983 Trustee and chairman of admissions committee, Bennington College, Vermont
1980-1988 Senior consultant, Academy for Educational Development
1981 Author, Higher Education in Twelve Countries: A Comparative View
1982-1985 Research grantee, Corporate Classrooms, Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching
1985 Author, Corporate Classrooms
1985-1986 Director, Consultant Team, Academy of Computer Science and Engineering, AT&T Bell Laboratories
1986-1990 Research grantee, The Learning Industry (director of the Adult Learning Project), Carnegie Foundation for Advancement of Teaching
1986-1990 Member of editorial board, Industry and Higher Education, published by Butterworth & Co. Publishers
1987-1988 Advisor, Committee on Career-Long Education for Engineers (CLEFE), National Academy of Engineering
1987-1990 Member, Advisory Board, Alliance for Learning
1988 Married Maurice Lazarus
1988-1990 Member, Board of Directors, International Council for Educational Development
1990 Author, The Learning Industry: Education for Adult Workers
1991- Academic Advisory Board, Cambridge College
2008 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
Nell Eurich, also known as Nell Plopper, Nell P. Hutchinson, and Nell E. Lazarus, was an author, professor, dean, and education consultant. The collection includes materials on topics such as adult education, higher education in the United States, education administration, career training, distance education and delivery systems, coeducation, and literacy. For a detailed container list and curriculum vitae provided by Nell Eurich, see the Collection overview and biographical file.
The Professional positions and activities file documents Eurich's career in education, including her role as a professor, education administrator, consultant, and member of various boards. Eurich was the dean of faculty and a professor of English at Vassar College from 1967 to 1970, a time when Vassar was transitioning to the coeducational model. This file includes information on the creation of the Black Studies Program, now known as the Africana Studies Program, and the Vassar-Yale Study. Additionally, the file includes documents related to New College in Sarasota, Florida, where Eurich served as a board member, and the Academy for Educational Development, where Eurich was a consultant.
In 1985, Eurich published Corporate Classrooms, the result of a study funded by the Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching. The book focused on training activities in large corporations, looking at the history, content, methodology, and means of delivery for corporate training. The Corporate Classrooms file contains drafts, notes, and research for the publication. As a result of that project, Eurich was asked to head the Adult Learning Project, a broader study to research adult education and training in the United States, focusing on economic productivity and the American work force. Funded by the Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching, the Adult Learners Project was directed by Eurich through the Academy for Educational Development (AED), where Eurich was a senior consultant. The aim of the study was to broaden the concept of adult education and training by looking at non-traditional means of education, such as corporations, proprietary schools, labor unions, trade associations, community colleges, the military, and the federal government. As a result of that study, The Learning Industry was published in 1990. The Learning Industry and Adult Learning Project file contains research, correspondence, and notes related to this project. The heading "missing persons," which became the title of a chapter in The Learning Industry, was used by Eurich to refer to people not employed in the work force or employed in part-time jobs without sufficient opportunities. Materials under the heading "other literature" consist of mainly printed matter, often in the form of flyers, brochures, or catalogs relating to a specific organization or event. Much of the correspondence and memoranda can be found in files with the heading "general."
The Other activities file documents Eurich's community service and other various pursuits. In 1941, Eurich was a participant in the International Student Service Summer Leadership Institute at Campobello Island, a program in which Eleanor Roosevelt opened up her summer home to thirty student leaders for lectures and discussion. Photographs of Eleanor Roosevelt can be found in box 120, folder 5.
The collection contains Eurich's Speeches and writings, including speeches discussing her book Corporate Classrooms and women in higher education. Also included are files on books and articles addressing topics in education.
General subject files, which include topics such as innovative education, coeducation, business, and higher education, can be found in the Education, training, and technology file.
Adult education.; Business and education.; Career education.; Education--United States.; Employees--Training of.; International education.; Occupational training.; Universities and colleges--United States.
- Education, training, and technology file
  - Business and industry
    - Conference Board
      - General, 1987, undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
      - Papers by Seymour Lusterman
        - "Education in Industry,", 1977 (Box-folder 1: 2)
        - "Managerial Competence: the Public Affairs Aspects", 1981 (Box-folder 1: 3)
        - "Trends in Corporate Training,", undated (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - Corporate training studies, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 1: 5)
    - Daverman Associates, 1986 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - Digital Equipment Corporation
      - Corporate training, education, and facilities division, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 1: 7)
      - Educational Services Management Conference (QUEST '87), 1987 (Box-folder 1: 8)
      - Proposal, Hubert Wilke, 1987, undated (Box-folder 1: 9)
    - Doctoral papers
      Scope and Contents note
      Includes correspondence and notes
      - Baker, Jeanette, "An Analysis of Degree Programs Offered by Selected Individual Corporations,", 1983-1987 (Box-folder 1: 10)
      - Hawthorne, Elizabeth, "The Emergence of Corporate Colleges,", 1983 (Box-folder 1: 11)
      - Morse, Suzanne, "Education Programs in Industry,", 1982-1983 (Box-folder 1: 12)
      - Pitre, Lee Frances, "Credit and Noncredit Opportunities Offered by Large Industrial Corporations,", 1980 (Box-folder 1: 13)
    - First Seminar Service, 1989-1993 (Box-folder 2: 1)
      Includes correspondence with John Tumminello
    - Fortune directory of U.S. corporations, 1983 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Hanfling, Martin, AIRCO Educational Services Division, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Humanics, Inc., 1986, undated (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - International Business Machines (IBM)
      - General, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 2: 5)
      - Leggett, Stan, report on IBM Midwest Education Center, 1967, 1986 (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - Institute for Corporate Education, 1987 (Box-folder 2: 7)
    - John Wiley & Sons, consultant Ronald Cohen, 1985 (Box-folder 2: 8)
    - Luxenberg, Stan, "Education at AT&T,", 1978-1979 (Box-folder 2: 9)
    - Martin Marietta Corporation
      - General, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 2: 10)
      - Work in America Institute, 1987 (Box-folder 2: 11)
    - National Alliance of Business publications, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 2: 12)
    - National Association of Private Industries Council, 1986 (Box-folder 2: 13)
    - Noble, Steven J., Human Resource Planning Society, 1989 (Box-folder 2: 14)
    - The Research Board, 1986, 1989 (Box-folder 2: 15)
    - Saul, Frank J., 1986 (Box-folder 2: 16)
    - Schmidt & Posner, "Managerial Values in Perspective,", 1983 (Box-folder 2: 17)
    - Shen Milsom & Wilke, Inc., 1989-1991 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - 3M, 1986, undated (Box-folder 3: 2)
    - Training/HRD, "U.S. Training Census & Trends Report,", 1982 (Box-folder 3: 3)
    - Western Behavioral Sciences Institute (WBSI), 1988, undated (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Partnerships
    - The Learning Industry, draft chapter and comments, 1988 (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - Bolivar project, Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching, 1975-1981 (Box-folder 3: 6)
    - Business-Higher Education Forum, 1995-1999 (Box-folder 3: 7)
    - Business-Higher Education Forum, 1982-1987 (Box-folder 3: 8)
- The Learning Industry and Adult Learning Project file
  - Research files for The Learning Industry
    - Occupations
      - Manufacturing
        - General, 1988 (Box-folder 4: 1)
        - Staff reports, 1988 (Box-folder 4: 2)
    - Target groups
      - Managers
        - Managers, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 4: 3)
        - Bureau of National Affairs report on management training and development programs, 1977 (Box-folder 4: 4)
      - Professionals
        - Memoranda, correspondence, and printed matter, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 4: 5)
        - Articles, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 4: 6)
        - Research studies on continuing education, 1982-1987 (Box-folder 4: 7)
        - Newsletters, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 4: 8)
        - Center for Professional Advancement, 1987-1988, undated (Box-folder 4: 9)
        - Continuing education, University of Georgia, 1985-1989 (Box-folder 4: 10)
        - LOMA Life Management Institute, 1986 (Box-folder 4: 11)
        - Maritime Institute of Technology, 1982-1988 (Box-folder 4: 12)
        - Occupations
          - Accountants
            - American Institute of Certified Public Accountants, printed matter, 1986-1989 (Box-folder 5: 2)
          - Bankers
            - General, 1986-1989 (Box-folder 5: 3)
            - American Institute of Banking, 1986-1989 (Box-folder 5: 4)
          - Engineers
            - General, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 5: 5)
            - Articles, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 5: 6)
            - Research studies, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 5: 7)
            - American Society for Engineering Education, printed matter, 1986 (Box-folder 5: 8)
            - National Academy of Engineering, 1988 (Box-folder 6: 1)
          - Lawyers
            - General, 1987 (Box-folder 6: 2)
            - Articles, 1983-1988 (Box-folder 6: 3)
            - Research studies
              - General, 1980-1984 (Box-folder 6: 4)
              - "A Plan for Lawyer Development" by Austin Anderson, 1985 (Box-folder 6: 5)
              - "An Overview of Continuing Legal Education" by Elizabeth Gee, 1987 (Box-folder 6: 6)
            - Printed matter
              - General, 1986-1987, undated (Box-folder 6: 7)
              - Arden House, 1958-1987 (Box-folder 7: 1)
              - Association of Continuing Legal Education Administration, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 7: 2)
              - American Institute for Law Training within the Office (AILTO), 1987 (Box-folder 7: 3)
  - Education
    - Vocational and technical
      - Other literature
        - National Association of Trade and Technical Schools (NATTS), 1985-1989 (Box-folder 7: 4)
        - National Home Study Council (NHSC), 1987-1988 (Box-folder 7: 5)
      - Proprietaries
        - Problems
          - Articles, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 8: 1)
          - Reports, 1984-1987 (Box-folder 8: 2)
          - Adelphi Institute, 1987 (Box-folder 8: 3)
        - Schools
          - ITT Educational Services, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 8: 4)
          - The Learning Annex, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 8: 5)
          - Macmillan, Inc., 1985-1987 (Box-folder 8: 6)
          - Microsoft University, 1988 (Box-folder 8: 7)
          - New York State schools, 1985-1987 (Box-folder 8: 8)
          - Organization for Rehabilitation through Training, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 8: 9)
          - Taylor Business Institute, 1987 (Box-folder 9: 1)
          - World Trade Institution Language School, 1987 (Box-folder 9: 2)
  - Federal government
    - Statistics, 1984-1987 (Box-folder 9: 3)
    - General, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 9: 4)
    - Articles, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 9: 5)
    - Research study by Howard Webber, 1987 (Box-folder 9: 6)
    - Research study commissioned by Ann Brassier, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 9: 7)
    - Other literature
      - "Employee Training in the Federal Service,", 1985 (Box-folder 9: 8)
      - Federal Training Excellence Network (FTEN), 1985-1986 (Box-folder 9: 9)
      - Interagency Group (IAG), 1986 (Box-folder 9: 10)
      - Training Officers Conference, 1986 (Box-folder 9: 11)
      - Tuition tax law, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 9: 12)
    - Programs
      - Support staff and managers
        - Department of Agriculture, graduate program, 1986, undated (Box-folder 10: 1)
        - Department of the Treasury, 1988 (Box-folder 10: 2)
        - General Services Administration (GSA)
          - Catalogs, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 10: 3)
          - Course flyers, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 10: 4)
        - Office of Personnel Management (OPM)
          - Printed matter, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 11: 1)
          - Federal Executive Institute, 1989 (Box-folder 11: 2)
          - Management Excellence Inventory, 1986 (Box-folder 11: 3)
        - Agencies, other branches, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 11: 4)
      - Missing persons
        - Report by Cynthia Greenleaf on public programs for employee training, 1988 (Box-folder 11: 5)
        - Federal Interagency Committee on Education, literacy management information report, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 11: 6)
        - Policy and legislation
          - Articles, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 11: 7)
          - Policy statements and debates, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 11: 8)
          - Reports on Job Training Partnership Act (JTPA) and Comprehensive Employment and Training Act (CETA) reports, 1981-1987 (Box-folder 12: 1)
          - Higher education amendments, 1986 (Box-folder 12: 2)
          - Literacy Corps, 1988-1991 (Box-folder 12: 3)
          - Perkins Vocational Education Act, 1987-1991 (Box-folder 12: 4)
          - Literacy bills, Simon (Senate) and Sawyer (House), 1989 (Box-folder 12: 5)
        - Welfare
          - Articles, 1986-1989 (Box-folder 12: 6)
          - Research studies, 1987 (Box-folder 12: 7)
      - Branch programs
        - Department of Commerce, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 12: 8)
        - Department of Education
          - Adult Education Program statistics, Adult Education Act, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 13: 1)
          - Adult education, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 13: 2)
          - Nevser, Stacy, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 13: 3)
          - Articles, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 13: 4)
          - Research studies, 1986-1987, undated (Box-folder 13: 5)
          - Other literature
            - Clearinghouse on Adult Education, 1987 (Box-folder 13: 6)
            - National Advisory Council on Adult Education, 1984-1985 (Box-folder 13: 7)
            - Adult Literacy Initiative, 1986 (Box-folder 13: 8)
        - Department of Labor
          - General, 1988 (Box-folder 13: 9)
          - David Barbee, Center for Advanced Learning Systems, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 13: 10)
          - Research studies, 1985-1988 (Box-folder 13: 11)
          - Unemployment insurance, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 13: 12)
          - Job Training Partnership Act (JTPA)
            - General, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 13: 13)
            - Articles, 1985-1989 (Box-folder 13: 14)
            - Research studies, 1986, undated (Box-folder 14: 1)
            - Federal research studies, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 14: 2)
  - Education
    - General
      - Articles, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 14: 3)
      - National University for Continuing Education Association/American Association for Adult and Continuing Education, 1988 (Box-folder 14: 4)
      - Peterson's guides, 1988 (Box-folder 14: 5)
      - Continuing education, 1987, undated (Box-folder 14: 6)
      - Continuing education at Harvard University, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 14: 7)
      - Liberal arts, 1987-1989 (Box-folder 14: 8)
      - Graduate study, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 14: 9)
      - Minorities in higher education, 1987-1988 (Box-folder 14: 10)
      - Student aid and tuition, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 14: 11)
    - Colleges and universities
      - Alverno College, Wisconsin, 1989 (Box-folder 15: 1)
      - Baruch College, New York, undated (Box-folder 15: 2)
      - Cambridge College, Massachusetts, 1988 (Box-folder 15: 3)
      - College for Human Services, New York/Florida/California, 1984 (Box-folder 15: 4)
      - Columbia University, New York, 1986-1988 (Box-folder 15: 5)
      - Empire State College, New York, 1988 (Box-folder 15: 6)